<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to two letters concerning the East-India Company</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32713</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12747677</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12747677</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93298</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25630)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93298)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1029:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to two letters concerning the East-India Company</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end:  Bristoll, the 30 June, 1676.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>East India Company.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  India.</term>
               <term>India --  Commerce --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93298:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO TWO LETTERS, CONCERNING THE EAST-INDIA COMPANY.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:93298:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93298:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN your laſt, I received two Letters in Print, Concerning the <hi>Eaſt India-Company;</hi> which, conſidering that you have been acquainted, how great a part of my Eſtate is entruſted to that <hi>Society,</hi> I cannot but take it as a Friendly Advertiſement; for which, be pleaſed to accept my Hearty Thanks. And I aſſure you, whatever my Sentiments are of the affair, I do and ſhall own it for an evident Demonſtration of your Affection, that in the midſt of your great Affairs, you ſhould be ſo mindfull of my Concerns.</p>
            <p>I have peruſed the ſaid Letters, and can ſee no reaſon to believe that ſuch Diſcourſes ſhould be publiſhed by any perſon whoſe Eſtate was entruſted to the ſaid <hi>Company;</hi> or that had any real deſire of receiving or giving ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction concerning the ſecurity of Money lent to them. No <hi>Creditor</hi> can be ſuppoſed to act ſo contrary to his own intereſt, as to make it his endeavour to weaken or leſſen his ſecurity, by Expoſing and Ruining his <hi>Debtors Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit;</hi> or teaching him a way to defraud himſelf, which is the Language of thoſe Papers. It muſt therefore be ſome other Perſon then a <hi>Creditor,</hi> and ſome other Deſign than a doubt about <hi>Security,</hi> that occaſioned the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing theſe Letters. There hath been a report that the <hi>Dutch</hi> had in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to propoſe at the <hi>Treaty</hi> at <hi>Nimegen,</hi> a Reſtraint of the Importation of <hi>Callico</hi> into <hi>Europe,</hi> becauſe it hinders the conſumption of <hi>French, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Flanders,</hi> and <hi>German Linnens:</hi> And lately ſome here did Decry the <hi>Eaſt-India-Company</hi> and Trade, becauſe <hi>Callico</hi> (as they ſaid) hindred the vent of <hi>Fuſtians</hi> and ſome other Native Manufactures. Theſe correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponding ſo exactly, give ground to think they proceed from the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and the <hi>Authour</hi> of theſe Letters may be of that <hi>Caball.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He firſt endeavours to deſtroy the <hi>Credit</hi> of the <hi>Company,</hi> by telling us, <hi>That their Seal is leſs ſecurity, than the word of any one ſufficient man among them; for that not any one of the Companies Perſons or Eſtates,</hi> (he meanes beſide what is in the joynt ſtock of the Company) <hi>whether Real or Perſonal is thereby bound,</hi> neither <hi>can any of them be arreſted or impleaded by virtue thereof,</hi> Who is there ſo ignorant, but knowes this? though the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> ſuppoſeth all are ſuch Fools, that have lent money to the Company, that they were <hi>like fiſh drawn into the Net, by vainly imagining that every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the Company in his Particular and Private capacity was bound to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for the ſame.</hi> I dare ſay not one of forty that have lent money to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93298:3"/>the <hi>Company</hi> thought ſo. I have heard indeed of one that had a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſumme there, who upon the advice of ſome <hi>Councel</hi> of this <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Capacity, demanded his money, which being preſently paid him by the <hi>Eaſt-India-Company,</hi> he lodged it in <hi>Lombardſtreet,</hi> where it lyes (and is like toly) till the opening of the Exchequer. I ſuppoſe he rendered the <hi>GEntleman</hi> no thanks for his advice, nor accounts himſelf the wiſer man for following it. If it be ſeriouſly conſidered, on what grounds, perſons have choſen to put their money into the <hi>Eaſt-India-Companies</hi> hands, rather than to entruſt it elſewhere; it will appear they were no ſuch Fools, as they are character'd for, nor the Security ſo ſlight, as the <hi>Gentleman</hi> would have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it to be.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Gentleman preferrs a ſufficient mans word,</hi> (I will ſuppoſe his bond which is more valid, in regard of the uncertainty of life.) It's difficult to know who is <hi>ſufficient;</hi> all is not Gold that gliſters, or every man <hi>ſufficient</hi> that is thought ſo. If he be <hi>ſufficient</hi> when you lend the money, who can aſſure himſelf, he will Continue either <hi>ſufficient,</hi> or <hi>honeſt.</hi> Men are change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and their Eſtates ſubject to accidents. Doth not experience evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that loſſes at ſea, loſſes by fire, loſſes by bad debts, and other Caſualties, have rendred <hi>Perſons</hi> inſolvent, that had great <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,</hi> as alſo that ſometimes <hi>Perſons</hi> have purchaſed lands in their <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens</hi> names, and otherwiſe ſo conveyed away their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> that their <hi>Creditors</hi> could never reach them; and if they ſeize their Perſons they can live in the <hi>Rules,</hi> and laugh at their <hi>Creditors.</hi> As for lending money on <hi>Mortgages</hi> and <hi>real ſecurity,</hi> which is eſteemed the beſt <hi>ſecurity;</hi> Is it not very troubleſome to attend on <hi>Councell,</hi> to examine <hi>Titles,</hi> to make <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances?</hi> And when all is done with the greateſt advice and circumſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; is it not very hazardous, in regard of bad <hi>Titles, Dormant Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances,</hi> and <hi>Precontracts?</hi> can the moſt eminent and ſubtile <hi>Lawyers</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure themſelves? have ot ſome of them been over-reached? And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when the ſecurity is good as to the main; yet what difficulty, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vexation is there to arrive at ſatisfaction, by attending long <hi>Sutes</hi> in <hi>Chancery,</hi> accounting for profits, The <hi>Creditor</hi> being often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times made the Debtors ſteward, and that without Salary or Compenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for his pains. And on ſuch <hi>Securities</hi> who can depend on his money to anſwer his Occaſions.</p>
            <p>If he have a <hi>Daughter</hi> to <hi>Marry,</hi> a Son to preferre in <hi>Trade,</hi> or a <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe</hi> to make, all his deſigns are fruſtrated, His money being (if not in Hell unretreviable, yet) in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> whence it cannot be delivered but in a long Tract of time, and that by patient undergoing the ſmarting Torment of Tedious and Chargeable Sutes. It muſt be acknowledged, that there
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93298:3"/>is no abſolute certainty or aſſurance of any thing in this World; and whoever believes otherwiſe, is gone beyond the bounds of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion;</hi> and fit only to reſide in the new <hi>Palace</hi> in <hi>Moorfields.</hi> All that can be deſired in the putting out of money, is to have a viſible <hi>fond</hi> engaged, that is <hi>morally</hi> (not only at the time of lending) moſt ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſecure it, but alſo in probability moſt likely to continue ſo, and to anſwer the Occaſions of the Lender.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then, They that lend Money to the <hi>Eaſt India-Company,</hi> on their <hi>Common Seal,</hi> have a viſible <hi>fond</hi> engaged that is ſufficient to ſecure the ſame. Though the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Company</hi> are neither reſponſible in their Perſons, nor private Eſtates for what is taken up thereupon, yet all the Moneys, Goods, and Effects belonging to the <hi>Joynt ſtock</hi> of the <hi>Company</hi> are engaged, as the Gentleman himſelf is neceſſitated to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. His inſinuations concerning the caſe of the <hi>Merchant-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers,</hi> and <hi>Grocers Company,</hi> are not to the purpoſe; thoſe <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> never had any <hi>Joint-ſtock,</hi> as a viſible <hi>fund</hi> to ſecure what they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, but were truſted upon their bare Reputation and Credit. It is farre otherwiſe here. Suppoſe there hath been lent to the <hi>Enſt-Iudia-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> 5 or 600 thouſand pound, the Lenders either do or might know, that there is in the <hi>Joint-ſtock</hi> of the ſaid Company in real value upwards of 900 thouſand pound, (I may ſay a <hi>Million</hi> of pounds <hi>ſterling</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their dead ſtock, which is alſo conſiderable. All which, being toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>Million</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> of <hi>pounds ſterling,</hi> ſtands by their <hi>Common Seal</hi> bound and engaged to pay their <hi>Creditors.</hi> The <hi>Gentleman</hi> doth Ignorantly, if not Malitiouſly aſſert, pag. 4. That the <hi>Eaſt-India-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany trades wholly with their Creditors Money, and that it's ſeldome that they have above</hi> 600 <hi>thouſand pounds in value in their India Factories, and on the Seas at the ſame time.</hi> To demonſtrate the falſity of which, take but an account of what they ſent out this laſt year, and it will be found to be upwards of 450 thouſand pounds: And to that adde the value of the 3 <hi>Ships</hi> already arrived this year from <hi>Bantam;</hi> and the 5 <hi>Ships</hi> from <hi>Surrat;</hi> with the other 6 or 7 <hi>Ships</hi> expected from the <hi>Coaſt Surrat</hi> and <hi>Bantam,</hi> which will amount at leaſt to 800 <hi>thouſand pounds</hi> (and as Sales may prove, to a great deal more) ſo that there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to have been above 12 <hi>hundred thouſand pounds value</hi> on the Seas at one time, beſide all the remains of Goods and Debts in <hi>India</hi> and in <hi>England.</hi> There being then ſuch a <hi>ſtock,</hi> it cannot be denyed but that there is a viſible and ſufficient <hi>fond</hi> to ſecure the Creditors the Moneys that they have lent. But the <hi>Gentleman</hi> tells us, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. <hi>The Indians or Infidels may deſtroy their Factories, and Goods in India;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93298:4"/>their Ships and Cargo's may be loſt or taken in Warr, or by Pirates, and the Company may make a Divident to ſecure their own Eſtates, and leave the Creditors to find a thing in the Clouds.</hi> Therefore it will be neceſſary in the next place to evidence that the <hi>joynt ſtock</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt-India-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> is on Morall and Rational grounds, moſt likely to continue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſecure the moneys lent thereupon. That which might render it inſufficient according to the <hi>Gentlemans</hi> ſuggeſtions, is either loſſes arriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Forreign accidents, or diſhoneſt practices either by concealment, or by making dividents of the <hi>ſtock</hi> amongſt the Members of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> without regard to the payment of the Debtors.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to Caſualties, whereby loſſes may happen to the ſtock; The Gentleman mentions a Concatenation of Evils, <hi>Deſtruction</hi> from the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, Loſſes</hi> by <hi>Stormes,</hi> by <hi>War</hi> and by <hi>Pirates.</hi> Should we wrack our fancies to find out, and then ſuffer our thoughts to dwell on the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the accidents that may fall out in Humane affaires, we ſhould never enjoy quiet in our Mindes; or elſe we ſhould be deterred from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving or ſetting upon any affair. For as the wiſe man tells us, <hi>He that obſerves the Wind ſhall not Sow, and he that regardeth the Clouds ſhall not Reap.</hi> It is ſufficient, that we take the moſt probable ways of Security, and leave the reſt to Divine Providence. Now if we conſider the affaires of the <hi>Eaſt-India-Company</hi> without prejudice, we cannot but conclude that their <hi>ſtock</hi> of 1600 <hi>thouſand pounds,</hi> will always be ſufficient to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer 600 <hi>thouſand pounds.</hi> For the whole at no time, is hazarded in one bottom, as it often falls out in private mens dealings; Some part is in <hi>England</hi> in Goods and Debts, ſome part in <hi>India</hi> in Trade and Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, and ſome part is at Sea, Going and Coming; not in one Ship but in 30 Ships or more, not in one Courſe or Voyage, but in ſeveral: So that though a loſs ſhould happen to ſome part, yet in the ordinary courſe of providence, there is Rational ground to believe there would be alwayes enough preſerved to anſwer the Engagements.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. As to diſhoneſt practices, is it Rationally to be ſuppoſed that a Number of men can ſo eaſily engage in wicked and cheating actions? The <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt-India ſtock</hi> is committed to 26 <hi>Perſons,</hi> and no Affair can be Tranſacted without 13, ſo that if the Major part be Perſons of Honeſty and Conſcience, you are ſecure; nothing can be done unworthily. Yea if there ſhould be but one Honeſt man of 13, yet you are ſure, ſeeing ſuch an act of knavery, as would defraud the <hi>Creditors,</hi> would be detected. The <hi>Gentleman</hi> tell us, (<hi>pag.</hi> 3.) <hi>You may ſue the Company on their common Seal, and have Execution againſt their Goods, but then asks where ſhall you find the Goods of the Company to pay</hi> 5 s.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93298:4"/>
               <hi>in the pound:</hi> and withall addes, <hi>That were there Goods of a greater value, the Company may divide them amongſt themſelves, and ſo the Creditors have never a penny, unleſs they can catch it in the</hi> Indies.</p>
            <p>Since the Eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> in this preſent <hi>joynt-ſtock,</hi> which is now neer nineteen years, was ever any perſon that lent Money to the <hi>Company</hi> on their <hi>common</hi> Seal, forced to ſue them? Have not all men been payd their Money readily whenever they demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it?</p>
            <p>How is it poſſible that the <hi>Companyes</hi> goods ſhould be concealed, that muſt paſs through ſo many hands, and are in ſuch vaſt quantities, and of ſuch ſorts as may eaſily be diſtinguiſhed from others? It hath been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a <hi>Maxim</hi> amongſt the <hi>Committee</hi> of that <hi>Company</hi> (as I have heard) never to take up more money at Intereſt, than they had reall Effects in <hi>England,</hi> in Debts or Goods to ſatisfie. If for the laſt two years they have exceeded, to expatiate and extend the <hi>Trade</hi> for the Benefit of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> It is however but for a very ſmall time that it is otherwiſe, for at the arrival of their Ships from <hi>India</hi> in <hi>June, July,</hi> and <hi>Auguſt,</hi> they have conſtantly a vaſt Eſtate in <hi>England</hi> over and above what will anſwer all their Debts. And if there be not alwayes ſo much at the latter end of <hi>March,</hi> when their Ships are diſpeeded for <hi>India;</hi> in a few months after, when the former years Ships return, there is an abuudant Surpluſage. So that if it ſhould fall out (which never yet hath done, nor is it probable it ſhould) that any perſon ſhould ſue the <hi>Company</hi> for Money lent them at Intereſt on their <hi>common Seal,</hi> and Execution againſt their Goods ſhould be obtained, I ſay in ſuch a Caſe every perſon concerned, might eaſily and without any difficulty find Effects in <hi>England,</hi> to diſcharge all he can claim or challenge, nor is he left to <hi>find a thing in the Clouds, nor yet ſend to India to catch it;</hi> which Expreſſions the <hi>Gentleman</hi> might well have ſpared.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Company</hi> ſhould make a <hi>Divident</hi> among themſelves of their Goods and Eſtate, to defraud their <hi>Creditors,</hi> is not onely very <hi>unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably,</hi> but alſo very <hi>irrationally</hi> ſuggeſted. No <hi>Dividend</hi> can be made but by the <hi>Committee</hi> which (as before noted) conſiſts of 26 <hi>Perſons,</hi> and thoſe (or at leaſt moſt of them) of the beſt <hi>Reputation</hi> for <hi>honeſty</hi> and <hi>integrity</hi> in the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and can it be in Charity ſuppoſed, that they would joyn in ſuch an Act? I am confident they do abominate the thoughts of it. Beſides it is not in the power of the <hi>Committee,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Conſtitution, to make any <hi>Dividend</hi> in <hi>Goods.</hi> All <hi>Dividends</hi> are to be made in <hi>Money,</hi> and <hi>Goods</hi> are not to be ſold by <hi>private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract,</hi> but at a <hi>publick Sale.</hi> So that it is impoſſible, according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93298:5"/>
               <hi>Rules</hi> and conſtitution of the <hi>Company,</hi> that any <hi>Dividend</hi> can be made to the prejudice of the <hi>Creditors,</hi> but they muſt have ſufficient no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof, and may ſecure themſelves. But could it be imagined, that ſuch <hi>Dividends</hi> might be made, and that the <hi>Committee</hi> ſhould ſo far degenerate from all Principles of Honeſty, yet notwithſtanding what the <hi>Gentleman</hi> inſinuates, <hi>viz.</hi> That this might be done ſo as to leave the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor</hi> remedileſs in <hi>Law,</hi> I cannot believe, but rather think, the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> is miſtaken, and that he hath not well ſtudied or conſidered the Caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N.</hi> lends 1000 <hi>l.</hi> to the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> on their <hi>common Seal,</hi> on this ground, that there is at that time a joynt-ſtock of the Companyes, of the value of 900 thouſand pounds to ſecure and anſwer his Debt; the <hi>Committee</hi> divide this <hi>Stock</hi> of 900 thouſand pounds (after the lending of the Money) amongſt themſelves and other the Members of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: I now enquire, whether the <hi>Committee</hi> that made this <hi>Divident,</hi> be not in their own <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> obliged in Law or Equity to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Debt to <hi>N.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>N.</hi> did not truſt his Money on a vain Fancy, that the <hi>individual Members</hi> of the <hi>Company</hi> were in their private Capacities obliged to reſpond for his Money, but on this Foundation, That the <hi>joint-ſtock</hi> of the <hi>Company</hi> was to be his Security and <hi>guarant.</hi> This <hi>joint-ſtock</hi> was entruſted into the hands of the <hi>Committee</hi> to manage for the Benefit of the <hi>Adventurers,</hi> before they took up Money at Intereſt; but when they had taken up Money at Intereſt, then the <hi>joynt-ſtock</hi> is in the hands of the <hi>Committee</hi> in truſt, in the firſt place to anſwer and ſatisfie the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys taken up at intereſt: So that now the <hi>Committee</hi> are <hi>Truſtees</hi> for <hi>N.</hi> till his Debt be payd. If Loſſes and Accidents in the Courſe of Trade ſhould render the Stock incapable to anſwer the money to <hi>N.</hi> he muſt be content to ſit down by the loſs; but if the Committee by any wilfull act of theirs diſpoſe of the <hi>Stock,</hi> and convert it to their private uſe, before they have payd <hi>N,</hi> they are guilty of breach of truſt, and thereby have rendred themſelves anſwerable in their own <hi>private capacities</hi> to make ſatisfaction to <hi>N.</hi> This was the opinion of one of the moſt eminent and famous <hi>Lawyers</hi> of his time; (Serjeant <hi>Glyn;</hi>) and it ſeems ſo rational, that I am eaſily perſwaded to believe it to be ſo. And were it but a doubtfull Caſe, would it not be a moſt imprudent act of the <hi>Committee,</hi> to divide the <hi>Stock</hi> among the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Company,</hi> and expoſe themſelves in their own <hi>private capacities</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> to anſwer the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors,</hi> or at leaſt to be liable to Suits and Moleſtations.</p>
            <p>As to what the Gentleman obſerves, (<hi>p.</hi> 4.) <hi>That the King who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93298:5"/>the Company to uſe a common Seal, thought it not ſufficient ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for his Cuſtoms:</hi> But provided in their Patent that <hi>they ſhould give good and ſufficient bond with ſurety for the payment thereof.</hi> However, whether it be ſo, or no, in the Patent, I know not; But this I'm well aſſured of, that it ſerves little to the purpoſe he intends it; it being evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that thoſe words were not inſerted out of any doubt that either the <hi>King</hi> or his <hi>Miniſters</hi> had of the <hi>Companyes</hi> ſecurity by their <hi>common-Seal,</hi> but put in as words of courſe, a form uſual in ſuch caſes, for that the Kings Officers have never refuſed, but alwayes readily accepted the <hi>Companyes</hi> Obligation by their <hi>common Seal,</hi> for the payment of the <hi>Cuſtoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Gentleman</hi> believes, as he tells us, (<hi>pag.</hi> 5.) That <hi>the Company had never been ſuch Bankers, as to have deſerved Court Letters about their Officers, if they had given Bond with Sureties for the Money they have borrowed.</hi> (p. 2.) It ſeems what paſſed between the <hi>Court</hi> and the <hi>Company,</hi> was not ſuch a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> but he would have one fling at it. To this he ſubjoyns a fooliſh inſignificant pity, in reference to the <hi>Lombard-ſtreet Bankers,</hi> to which I ſay, that as I leave him to his own belief, ſo for his pity, I am ſure I ſhall never need it, upon the account of lending my money to the <hi>Company.</hi> Nor did the <hi>Gentlemans</hi> Friend deſerve a reproof, for not adviſing with him before he parted with his money to the Company, though he might have had it ſo unuſually cheap. For he may (if he have not already) receive his money from the <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> when he pleaſeth: But when he hath ſo done, he will be at a loſs to find-where he may place it upon ſuch rational grounds for ſecurity, it being evident by what hath been ſaid, That there is ſuch a viſible <hi>Fond</hi> engaged by the Companyes Seal, that is not onely more ſufficient at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but alſo more likely to continue ſo, to anſwer the Occaſions of the Lender, than is any where elſe at this time in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Gentleman</hi> in the next place, that he may effectually carry on his Deſign, having inſinuated <hi>p.</hi> 5. That the <hi>Company hath no firm legal Foundation, and ſo was in no probability of ſtanding,</hi> gives us a <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript</hi> of ſome Clauſes in the <hi>Companies Charter,</hi> and then takes the liberty to arraign the <hi>Kings Grant;</hi> Calls it a <hi>Monopoly,</hi> and <hi>a Monopoly of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolies;</hi> Quotes the <hi>Statute</hi> of 21 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 3. cites ſome <hi>Law-caſes;</hi> talks of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> and <hi>French Vaſſals;</hi> tells us, that he wonders, yea <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts that he is aſtoniſhed,</hi> to think <hi>how any durſt draw ſuch a patent;</hi> To omit other expreſſions of the like, if not a worſe complexion.</p>
            <p>It would be improper for me, who you know am no Lawyer, to take upon me to anſwer theſe matters. The Gentleman is pleaſed to name
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93298:6"/>Mr. <hi>Solliciter,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Attorney General,</hi> and they are able to do it to purpoſe. However I am perſwaded, notwithſtanding all the bluſter and noiſe he makes, his zeal in the Deſign (rather than in his profeſſion) hath carried him beyond his underſtanding, and that he is miſtaken in the whole matter. He quotes the Statute of 21 <hi>Jac. c.</hi> 3. as the Devil doth Scripture by halfes; for in the ſaid Statute it is thus expreſſed. <hi>Provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo, and it is hereby further intended, declared, and enacted, that this Act, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not in any wiſe extend, or be prejudiciall to the City of</hi> London, <hi>or to any City, Burrough, or Town Corporate within this Realm, for or concerning any Grants, Charters, or Letters Patents, to them or any of them, made or granted, or for or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, any Cuſtome or Cuſtomes, uſed by or within them or any of them, Or to any Corporations or Fellowſhips of any Art Occupation or Myſtery, or to any Companies or Societies of Merchants within this Realm, Erected for the Maintenance, Enlargement, or Ordering of any Trade of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. But that the ſame Charters, Cuſtomes, Corporations, Companies, Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhips and Societies, and their Liberties, Priviledges, Powers and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities, ſhall be, and continue of ſuch Force and Effect, as they were before the making of the Act, and of none other, Any thing before in this Act contained to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi> At the time of the making that <hi>Act,</hi> the <hi>Eaſt-India-Company</hi> was in being, by virtue of a <hi>Charter</hi> granted to them by King <hi>Jams</hi> not much differing from the preſent <hi>Patent</hi> (as I am informed,) And by the aboveſaid <hi>proviſo,</hi> the Parliament did Confirme and Allow, rather than Cenſure the ſame.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Gentleman</hi> gives us a Definition of a <hi>Monopoly,</hi> and then tells us (<hi>pag.</hi> 6.) <hi>the Statute provides that all Perſons, Bodies Politick and Corporate, which then were or thence after ſhould be, ſhould ſtand, and be diſabled, to have uſe, or exerciſe, or put in uſe any ſuch Monopolies.</hi> The word <hi>ſuch,</hi> is not in the <hi>Statute</hi> in that place; and if we take the ſubſequent words in that Statute, to Define or Explain what a <hi>Monopoly</hi> is; It refers only to matters within the <hi>Realm,</hi> which will not concern the preſent caſe. But ſuppoſe the Definition the <hi>Gentleman</hi> gives of a <hi>Monopoly</hi> were as he expreſſeth it (by the Law-books) to be <hi>an inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution or Allowance, by the King, by his Grant, Commiſſion or otherwiſe, to any Perſon, Body Politick or Corporate, of or for the only buying, ſelling, or uſing of any thing, whereby any Perſon or Perſons are ſought to be reſtrained of any Freedome or Liberty which they had before, or hindred in their lawfull Trade and Traffick.</hi> May we not underſtand this to be within the <hi>Kingdome</hi> onely, for can any Subject of <hi>England</hi> law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Trade or Traffick with any <hi>Forrein Nation,</hi> without the allowance
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93298:6"/>of the <hi>King,</hi> who hath the undoubted Prerogative of making War and Peace, upon which the ſame depends. I ſhall readily grant that as the <hi>King</hi> is Common Father of all his Subjects, ſo his Care and Protection of, and Proviſion for them, is in the General Equally and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently to be extended. But in ſome Caſes, and under ſome Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, hath not his <hi>Majeſty</hi> a Prerogative (nay, ought he not on the ſame right of Fatherhood) as to prefer the <hi>General</hi> Benefit, to that of <hi>Particular;</hi> ſo ſometimes to extend ſpeciall <hi>Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Grants</hi> to ſome <hi>Particulars</hi> for the <hi>General Benefit,</hi> though other particulars may ſeem to receive prejudice thereby? Is not this the caſe of moſt of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations in <hi>England?</hi> which yet neither our <hi>Barriſter</hi> nor any other will account <hi>Monopolies.</hi> And that this is alſo the caſe of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, will appear when it is conſidered, that this <hi>Trade</hi> is not to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged and carried on for the <hi>General Benefit</hi> and Profit of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> ſo well in any other way as by a <hi>Company</hi> in a <hi>Joint-ſtock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, if a <hi>Monopoly be a reſtraining of Perſons from the freedome or Liberty they had before:</hi> I ask whether ever the People generally had the Freedome and Liberty of the <hi>Eaſt-India Trade?</hi> Except it was in the late unhappy times from 1653 to 1657? In which little time the Trade was almoſt totally ruined as to the Nation, The Experience where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of neceſſitated the then Powers, with the univerſall good liking and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of all perſons, to reſettle the Company.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe a <hi>Countrey</hi> that was <hi>undiſcovered,</hi> or a <hi>Countrey</hi> that for the <hi>difficulty of paſſage</hi> to it, or <hi>chargeableneſs</hi> and <hi>hazard</hi> of the <hi>adventure,</hi> no <hi>Eugliſh</hi> had traded to formerly; and that ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> men at their own <hi>Hazard</hi> and <hi>Charges</hi> ſhould <hi>diſcover</hi> the <hi>One, Purchaſe</hi> land of the <hi>Natives, Settle</hi> a <hi>Collony,</hi> and <hi>Eſtabliſh</hi> a <hi>Trade;</hi> and on the <hi>Other</hi> after great hazards and Adventures, with vaſt Charges and Expences, arrive to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a profitable Trade, and by preſents obtain Liberty of Trade from the <hi>Prince</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Countrey,</hi> Peculiarly for Themſelves and their Aſſigns: May not the <hi>King</hi> by his <hi>Prerogative</hi> Confirm thoſe <hi>Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulations,</hi> and grant the <hi>Priviledge</hi> of the Trade to the <hi>Diſcoverers</hi> and <hi>Adventurers,</hi> and their <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> thereby to encourage others to the like Noble undertakings, for the Generall good of his Kingdome? How could ſuch a <hi>Grant</hi> be within the Compaſs of a <hi>Monopoly,</hi> Since no <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> man was denied or debarred of any Liberty that he before exerciſed or enjoy'd? Is there any thing more reaſonable, than that they who at a vaſt Charge, with great Hazard and Difficulty purchaſed a trade, ſhould have the enjoyment of it? <hi>Shall not he that planteth a Vineyard eat the fruit thereof?</hi> And what can be more unjuſt than that another ſhould come in and reap the fruits of my Atchievements, that was either
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93298:7"/>idle, ignorant, or afraid; that knew not, would not, or durſt not adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to obtain the ſame? May there not be a right of <hi>Propriety</hi> in a <hi>Trade,</hi> as well as in <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Houſes?</hi> this is the Caſe of the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> in a great meaſure.</p>
            <p>Further, Suppoſe there be a <hi>known Trade,</hi> that may be very <hi>advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and that for the <hi>obtaining</hi> and <hi>ſettling,</hi> and <hi>carrying</hi> on of which there is a neceſſity to be at a vaſt <hi>Expence,</hi> to ſettle and keep <hi>Factories</hi> and <hi>Agents</hi> in ſeveral places, and with ſeveral <hi>Princes,</hi> and on Occaſion by <hi>Warre</hi> to <hi>force</hi> thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> to perform their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulations,</hi> and to erect <hi>Forts</hi> and maintain <hi>Garriſons</hi> for ſecurity of the Trade, as alſo to <hi>cope</hi> with and prevent the deſigns of Enemies that would debarre the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of ſuch a Trade; all which could not be done, but on a <hi>publick Charge</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> by ſome <hi>General Tax,</hi> or by ſome <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Body of Men</hi> encouraged to undertake the ſame by <hi>ſpecial Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges</hi> and <hi>Immunities,</hi> granted to <hi>them</hi> and their <hi>Succeſſors;</hi> Suppoſe I ſay in ſuch a Caſe that the <hi>King,</hi> to compaſs the obtaining and carrying on of ſuch a Trade for the <hi>General</hi> benefit of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> without a <hi>Tax</hi> on his <hi>People,</hi> ſhould <hi>propoſe</hi> to <hi>give</hi> and <hi>grant</hi> to all his <hi>Subjects,</hi> that would voluntarily unite their <hi>Stocks</hi> in ſuch an Affair, certain <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges</hi> and <hi>Immunities,</hi> and amongſt others the ſole enjoyment of the Trade of ſuch places to them and theirs, excluding all others that ſhould refuſe to joyn therein. On ſuch an <hi>invitation</hi> and Propoſal freely <hi>offered</hi> to all without <hi>exception,</hi> onely a <hi>certain</hi> number of <hi>perſons come</hi> in, <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> the <hi>Terms,</hi> and <hi>receive</hi> the <hi>Grant</hi> confirmed and ſettled, under the <hi>Broad-Seal</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> In ſome Proceſs of time, after great hazards and vaſt Expences to the Undertakers and Adventures, the Trade proving more advantageous and profitable to the particulars intereſſed, than at firſt was apprehended it would; Thoſe others that would not intermeddle at firſt, make great exclamations becauſe they are excluded, <hi>Crye</hi> out a <hi>Monopoly,</hi> a reſtraining the Subject the freedom and liberty of Trade. Have they any reaſon ſo to doe? was not the fault their own? It was free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tendred to them, they had the liberty to have come in on the ſame terms that others did: Shall they that voluntarily excluded themſelves, be angry that they are excluded, and charge it as a Crime either on the <hi>King</hi> that invited them, or on their fellow-Subjects that would at firſt have been glad of their aſſiſtance? Is not this moſt unjuſt and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able? This is the Caſe of thoſe that ſo highly exclaim againſt the <hi>Eaſt-India Company,</hi> which I ſuppoſe being rightly underſtood, the <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes Charter</hi> will not deſerve the name of a <hi>Monopoly;</hi> nor ſhall the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyes Creditors</hi> need to ſear that the Company ſhould be rendered In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93298:7"/>to pay their Debts, by <hi>being condemn'd in Treble dammages, or fined at the Common Laws for accepting ſuch a Patent,</hi> (p. 9.) to which our Barriſter, without underſtanding, (if not without conſulting his Books) thinks them lyable.</p>
            <p>The Gentleman in the cloſe of his Letter would inſinuate, that the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade is of no Benefit to the Nation, and if it were, yet that it might be more advantageouſly mannaged than by a Company in a Joynt-Stock. This I gueſs to be his meaning, but leſt I ſhould miſtake, I will repeat his own words, pag. 10. <hi>I that am no Trader know that the Parliament could, if it be an uſefull Trade to</hi> England, <hi>(which I am no proper Judge of) have eſtabliſhed legally ſuch Rules whereby the Trade, might have been managed, and Factories, Forts, and Caſtles maintained; and the liberty of Trade might have been preſerved to every Engliſh-man, and five times the trade gained, and the price of our own Manufactures of Cloath and others advanced, by the multitude and freedom of Buyers; and the price of the goods imported much leſſened to the Engliſh, and much more Trade with theſe Commodities gained into other parts of the World. An Inſtance of this is well known in the Turkey Company, where no Merchant can be excluded or denyed to trade with their particular Stock; yet the ſame pretence might have been for reſtraint, that ſome do vainly ſuggeſt in this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who is ſo bold as blind <hi>Bayard?</hi> they that know leaſt, are apt to think they know moſt. Ignorance and Confidence are often Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The Gentleman tells us, though he be no <hi>Trader, yet he knows.</hi> what doth he know? he doth not know whether the <hi>Trade</hi> to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> be an <hi>uſeful Trade</hi> to <hi>England;</hi> that he is not a proper Judge of, as he ſaith. He might with little ſtudy or obſervation have known, that it's a <hi>Trade</hi> all <hi>Nations</hi> have and do court at the higheſt rate: A <hi>Trade</hi> that the <hi>Dutch</hi> have adventured their All to purchaſe; A <hi>Trade</hi> which as it is carryed on onely by a <hi>Company</hi> in the way of <hi>Joynt-ſtock,</hi> ſo the gain thereby accrewing, maintains the <hi>Republick</hi> in Honour, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Opulency; A <hi>Trade</hi> whereby they have ſo encreaſed to Riches and Strength, as almoſt to become Maſters of the World: A <hi>Trade</hi> wherein the <hi>Engliſh Company</hi> employ and maintain above forty Ships, from 3 to 500 Tuns, and upwards of 3000 <hi>Sea-men;</hi> a <hi>Trade</hi> that ſupplyes the <hi>Nation</hi> with neceſſary Commodities, at a tenth part of the price the Nation muſt otherwiſe pay for them. <hi>Pepper</hi> would be as dear as <hi>Nutmegs,</hi> if the <hi>Dutch</hi> were ſole Maſters of it; <hi>Callico</hi> muſt be ſupplyed by <hi>French, Dutch</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> Linnen; A <hi>Trade</hi> that makes us Maſters of the <hi>Salt-petre,</hi> enables us to defend our ſelves, frees our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93298:8"/>houſes from thoſe Vermin, (the Salt-petre-men) that dug up our roomes; A <hi>Trade</hi> that upholds our forreign Trades, by bringing us Commodities to carry abroad to <hi>France, Spain, Italy, and Turkey,</hi> to a farther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of our Navigation. A <hi>Trade</hi> that beſides the <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> to his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> which are very conſiderable, brings an <hi>Annual Addition,</hi> of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral 100000 pounds to the real <hi>Stock</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> There are beſides theſe, divers other advantages, too many to enumerate. All this is ſo perſpicuous, that the <hi>Gentleman</hi> might eaſily have diſcerned it, were his ſight clear, and not clouded by prejudice, or obſtructed by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention of ſome private (if not forrein) intereſt. But though he knows not whether the Trade be uſefull for <hi>England,</hi> yet he knows if it were, the <hi>Parliament could have eſtabliſhed ſuch rules, &amp;c.</hi> Excellent! how comes it to paſs the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath not done it all this while? The Reaſon is ſuggeſted, It was not an uſefull trade for <hi>England.</hi> But might it not have been made an uſefull Trade, If ſuch Rules had been made to have gained 5 times the Trade, to have advanced the price of our Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, and leſſened the price of Goods imported, and have gained much more trade into other parts of the World? Certainly the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath not been of the <hi>Gentlemans</hi> mind, neither to have Judged the Trade uſeleſs, For then they would have put it down; Nor yet to think that ſuch <hi>Rules</hi> as he Imagines could have been made to effect what he fancies, for then they would have eſtabliſhed them. The Gentleman might have done well for the Benefit of his Countrey (if he intended it) to have ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted (if he could) what theſe <hi>Rules</hi> were, that they might have been conſidered; and till he declares what <hi>Rules</hi> he means, I can make no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſtruction of his words, than that he knows that the Parliament, could have made ſuch Rules, though he knows not what. I Readily grant, the <hi>Parliament,</hi> (which is the Wiſdome, and Supream Authority of the Nation) can and will make all neceſſary rules for the good of the Kingdome, and to ſay ſuch Rules could have been made and yet never were, (though many <hi>Parliaments</hi> have been ſince the firſt Eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade) ſeems too much to reflect on that great Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. The <hi>Gentleman</hi> tells us, an <hi>inſtance of this is well known in the Turkey Company.</hi> An Inſtance of what? that the <hi>Parliament</hi> could have Eſtabliſhed ſuch <hi>Rules</hi> as to have gained 5 times, the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade? ſure that cannot be the meaning; the Parliament having never made any Rules, much leſs ſuch <hi>Rules</hi> for the <hi>Turkey Company.</hi> The Gentleman ſure was ſo aſtoniſhed, that he was in a <hi>Labyrinth,</hi> and loſt his ſenſes.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:93298:8"/>
            <p>To help him therefore out, though this be no Inſtance of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments making <hi>Rules,</hi> yet may it not be an Inſtance, that if the <hi>Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Company</hi> did admit all Merchants to trade with their particular Stocks, (as he ſaith the <hi>Turkey</hi> Company do, though therein he miſtakes; for its only their own Members that have liberty,) it would have increaſed and augmented the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade five times more than now it is? This certainly muſt be the thing he intended, yet I cannot find how it is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. The <hi>Turkey</hi> Company never were in a <hi>Joynt-ſtock</hi> (that not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo neceſſary and ſuitable to that Trade) ſo it could never be known what Increaſe the alteration from one to the other would have made; and it is evident, that the <hi>Eaſt-India Trade</hi> hath been more increaſed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged within theſe few years under a <hi>Joynt-ſtock,</hi> than the <hi>Turkey-trade</hi> hath been under a <hi>Regulation.</hi> It is alſo certain (as before noted) that the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade in three or four years time of open Trade was almoſt totally ruined, and could not have been upheld ſo much to the <hi>Intereſt</hi> and Benefit of the Kingdom, unleſs it had been reduced into a <hi>Company, and Joynt-ſtock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Inconfiſtency of maintaining and carrying on the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> trade in a Regulation without a Company and a Joynt ſtock, the great miſchief and ruine it might be to the Kingdom, both in point of Wealth and Strength (which includes all,) If we ſhould loſe or be cheated of that Trade, and what may be further done for the ſecuring and augmenting of it, are Subjects would require larger Diſcourſes than my time at preſent will admit of. I hope, Sir, what I have ſaid, may be enough to ſatisfie you, that the <hi>Joynt-ſtock</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> is a <hi>ſufficient ſecurity,</hi> and that the ſaid Company is neither ſo obnoxious, nor my ſelf or others that have lent Money to them, ſo ill adviſed, as the <hi>Gentleman</hi> in his Letter would inſinuate. This is all I intended in anſwer to yours.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Briſtoll</hi> 
                  <date>the 30 <hi>June,</hi> 1676.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:93298:9"/>
            <head>The Bookseller to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe coming accidentally to my hands, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſo far upon the Author, as without either his Authority or Permiſſion to commit it to the Preſs. If he be offended to find that offered to publick View, which he deſigned onely for the ſatisfaction of a private Friend, I ſhall ſay, that beſides its being a Vindication of a Society, all whoſe Meaſures are juſt and honourable, and their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings great and ſucceſſefull, it is a ſervice alſo to the Kingdom, to which ſo many Advantages are derived by them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93298:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93298:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93298:10"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
